In this lesson, you're going to learn
在这节课
about SVD as a traditional approach to matrix factorization.
你将学习矩阵分解的传统方法 SVD
Unfortunately, as you'll find out for yourself,
遗憾的是 你将发现
this approach will fall short,
这个方法
and helping us in making recommendations,
无法帮助我们做出推荐
as it only works when our user item matrix has no missing values.
因为只有在用户-项目矩阵没有缺少值时 它才有用
However, the ideas here will be helpful as we continue in the rest of the lesson.
但是 学到的概念有助于我们继续学习这节课剩下的内容
In the previous lesson,
在上节课
you saw how we might create a user item matrix with users on the rows like this,
我们创建了一个用户-项目矩阵
and items on the columns like this.
行表示用户 列表示项目
We might rewrite the user item matrix,
我们可以重写用户-项目矩阵
where each R represents the rating by some user for some item.
每个 r 表示某个用户对某个项目的评分
So, the first values,
前面的值 1-n
one through N indicate which user made the rating.
表示哪个用户发表的评分
The second value, one through M indicate the movie being rated.
后面的值 1-n 表示被评分的电影
So, R11 here represents the rating user one gave to movie one.
所以 r11 表示用户 1 对电影 1 的评分
R23 here represents the rating user two gave to movie three.
r23 表示用户 2 对电影 3 的评分
When we use singular value decomposition or SVD on a user item matrix,
当我们对用户-项目矩阵使用奇异值分解 (SVD) 时
we split it into three matrices.
我们将矩阵拆分为三个矩阵
Commonly, these matrices are called U Sigma and V transpose.
通常这些矩阵称为 U ∑ VT
First, let's take a closer look at this U matrix.
先来看看这个矩阵 U
The goal of this U matrix is to give us an idea of
矩阵 U 的作用是告诉我们
how users are related to particular latent factors.
用户与特定的潜在因子之间的关系
So, let's say we have these four users,
假设有这四个用户
and we'll also bring back a few latent factors: dogs, AI and sadness.
再添加几个潜在因子：狗、AI 和悲伤
Numbers within this U matrix would be an indicator of
这个 U 矩阵中的数字表示
how each user feels about each latent factor.
每个用户对每个潜在因子的感受
We can see that Jessie will rate dog movies highest.
可以看出 Jessie 对狗类电影的评分最高
We can also see how AI ratings are related to each user,
还可以看出 AI 评分与每个用户的关系
where Sam will rate these movies highest,
Sam 对这些电影的评分最高
or that these users will rate sad movies the highest.
这些用户对悲伤电影的评分最高
The U matrix would then be an N by K matrix,
U 矩阵是一个 n x k 矩阵
where K determines the number of latent factors you're looking to keep.
k 表示要保留的潜在因子数量
Next, let's take a look at the V transpose matrix.
接下来 我们来看看 V 转置矩阵
This matrix again holds all the latent factors.
这个矩阵也包含所有的潜在因子
But instead of users,
但是它涉及的是电影
this matrix tells us about movies.
而不是用户
Looking at the same latent factors but using the movies instead,
查看的是相同的潜在因子 但是用到的是电影
we get a matrix that looks like this.
我们获得了这样的矩阵
From the V transpose matrix,
从 V 转置矩阵可以看出
we can see that Lady and the Tramp has
《小姐与流浪汉》
the highest value associated with our dog latent feature.
在小狗潜在特征方面具有最高值
The Notebook is the saddest of our movies,
《恋恋笔记本》是最悲伤的电影
AI and Wall-E have positive values with our robot latent feature.
《人工智能》和《机器人瓦力》在机器人潜在特征方面的值很高
The Notebook and Lady and the Tramp have
《恋恋笔记本》和《小姐与流浪汉》
pretty large negative values associated with this feature,
在这个特征方面具有很小的负值
which brings up a good point.
这很合理
The values of the U and V transposed matrices can take on any value.
U 和 V 转置矩阵的值可以是任何值
The weighting of movies or users onto a particular latent feature do not need to be
电影或用户对特定的潜在特征的权重并不一定是正数
positive even if all the given ratings and the user item matrix are positive.
即使所有的评分和用户-项目矩阵值是正数
Given the information being held in this matrix,
根据这个矩阵包含的信息
we can see that it's a K by N matrix,
可以判断它是一个 k x n 矩阵
where K is the number of latent factors,
k 表示潜在因子的数量
and N is the number of movies.
n 表示电影数量
Finally, we also need to look at the middle Sigma matrix.
最后 我们还需要查看中间的 ∑ 矩阵
This matrix is a K by K diagonal matrix,
这是一个 k x k 对角矩阵
which means every entry that is not on the diagonal is a zero.
表示非对角线上的所有值都是 0
It has the same number of rows and
它的行数和列数
columns as the number of latent factors you decide to keep.
等于潜在因子的数量
In practice, the number of latent factors you
在实践中 潜在因子的数量
choose to keep isn't necessarily straightforward.
并不一定很直白
Here, we have these nicely labeled factors,
在此示例中 我们的潜在因子标记的很清晰
but you will see soon that won't really be the case.
但是很快你会发现现实中并非这样
These values along the diagonal can help us in
对角线上的值有助于我们判断
determining how many latent factors we keep.
要保留多少个潜在因子
They will always be positive values that are sorted from largest to smallest,
它们始终是从大到小排序的正数
where the first value is a weight associated with the first latent factor,
第一个值是与第一个潜在因子相关的权重
and the second value is associated with the second main factor and so on.
第二个值是与第二个潜在因子相关的权重 以此类推
The larger weights are an indication that the latent factor is more
权重越大 表示该潜在因子越重要
important and being able to reproduce the ratings of the original user item matrix.
能够重现原始用户-项目矩阵的评分
So, here we can see that knowing that a user has a strong preference for dogs,
对于这个示例 可以看出 在预测评分方面
or that a movie is related to dogs is more important in
用户很喜欢小狗或电影与小狗有关
predicting ratings than using preferences on robots or sadness.
比用户对机器人或悲伤电影的偏好程度更重要
By multiplying these matrices together,
通过将这些矩阵相乘
we are reconstructing a movie rating for
我们可以根据用户对潜在因子的感受
each user movie combination based on how the users feel about the latent factors,
以及这些潜在因子对于评分的重要性
as well as how much those latent factors matter towards a rating.
以及最后潜在因子出现在特定电影里的情况
Finally, using how a latent factor appears in a specific movie,
针对每个用户-电影组合重新构建一个电影评分
by finding values for the matrices U, sigma,
通过计算 U ∑ 和 V 转置矩阵的值
and V transpose, we can find a prediction for every user movie combination.
我们能够预测出每个用户-电影组合